John kiriak who would be truly belongs
in a hall of the pantheon of the the
greatest whistleblowers of this century
John was a CIA analyst who revealed and
more significantly confirmed rumors
of the U.S torture program in particular
the
waterboarding
techniques virtual drowning of
interrogation subjects
it was the first Insider to do that
could you imagine
Crossing that threshold to reveal
something like that knowing the
semi-trailer that's coming your way
but it was an issue the the torture
itself
some sort of mad
invention of Donald Rumsfeld so I I
imagine some Dark Fantasy that so
directly corrupted all that America had
stood for most profoundly corrupted all
that America stood for that prompted
John kiriaku to reveal
that program and of course there was
hell to pay he he went to jail but
beyond going to jail he lost uh
friendships he lost Korea he was mocked
and vilified and threatened and yet
through all of that he's still standing
and he's here today and he's in Julian
assandra's corner so uh John Curry
thank you very much and thank you very
much
I don't deserve it
first I want to thank Progressive
International and all the organizers for
the the opportunity to be here and to
address all of you this is a real thrill
for me it's a thrill because we're all
here for Julian Assange
that's how important this is and it's
important for several different reasons
I'm going to begin by asking for your
Indulgence and I apologize if you've
heard much of what I'm going to say
before
but I think it's important and it
deserves repeating
at the CIA they teach us in briefing
training to give your main point up
front so I'll do that
the American government is lying about
Julian Assange
that's the bottom line they're lying
and they're going to continue to lie
where do we even begin to talk about
this Julian has been charged with
multiple counts of Espionage Espionage
is the gravest offense or at least one
of the two gravest offenses with which a
person can be charged in the United
States in some cases it carries with it
the death penalty
I think that the justice department
wants us to be happy that they haven't
charged Julian with a death penalty
case within the Espionage Act but let's
talk about the Espionage Act for a
moment so you can see how ridiculous
this law is
the Espionage Act was written in 1917 to
combat German saboteurs during the first
world war it has never been updated in
any meaningful way
it does not even contain the term
classified information because the
classification system wasn't invented
until the 1950s
it says National Defense information but
then it never
defines what the term National Defense
information means it means whatever the
prosecution wants it to mean
many of us have argued over the years
that the Espionage Act is is
unconstitutionally Broad and vague
but we never get far enough in the court
system to actually make that case before
The Supreme Court Dan Ellsberg one of
the greatest heroes in modern America
tried and continues to try but we just
haven't quite made it that far
well the Espionage Act even though the
Congress has not taken it up to update
it
it was actually updated judicially in my
case at the time that this happened I
didn't realize how important it was
but uh in the very first hearing that I
had before my judge in 2012
my attorneys argued that
I did not have a Criminal Intent
when I spoke to the New York Times and
to ABC News my intent was to inform the
American people that the government was
committing a crime and by law in the
United States you cannot classify a
program if the program is Criminal you
cannot classify it for the purpose of
keeping the information from the
American people
my judge said that she would not just
reject that argument but she would
refuse to respect precedent that was set
in the case of Thomas Drake the NSA
whistleblower
she then looked at me and she said Mr
kiriaku you either did it or you didn't
do it and I think you did it
and that was it
so she defined Espionage in the context
of these cases very simply as providing
National Defense information to any
person not entitled to receive it
National Security journalists at the
Washington Post the New York Times The
Wall Street Journal and everywhere else
do that every single day
that's one of the reasons why this case
is so important
it's because and I don't mean to
overstate this the First Amendment of
the Constitution the freedom of speech
and the freedom of press is resting
on this case
if Julian Assange is successfully
prosecuted if he's convicted of
Espionage never mind the fact that he's
not even an American
but he's a journalist and a publisher
every journalist and publisher in
America
will be liable to this kind of
prosecution everybody will be facing
decades centuries maybe in prison
that's how dangerous this is
let's also look at what exactly it was
that Julian did Julian reported on war
crimes as I said a moment ago it is
illegal to classify a crime that's
actually a law in the federal code
it's never been prosecuted
right
why is it that CIA leaders were not
prosecuted when they created the torture
program
or when they created the illegal
extraordinary rendition program or when
they created the the secret prison
program
it's because they're the good guys
and you don't prosecute the good guys
when they're trying to keep us safe at
night
you remember the old saying about uh men
being willing to do dark things uh to
keep us safe
have we lost our Humanity it kind of
seems that way
another problem is that the United
States does not have an official Secrets
act thank God at least we don't have it
yet
but I can tell you that at the CIA they
like very much what they see in the UK
and their official Secrets Act
and so this is a way to sort of create
an official Secrets act through the back
door that if they can if they can
successfully prosecute Jillian Assange
they know that they can then prosecute
anybody
we're just going to have to take their
word for it that they don't want to
prosecute
the people that they believe to be
legitimate journalists
another issue and I say this all the
time but I do because it's true the
American people own the information that
Julian has released we have a right to
know what our country and our government
is doing in our name
I want to know if my government is
murdering journalists in Iraq I want to
know if my government is disappearing
people in secret prisons around the
world where nobody knows that they're
there and then they torture them in many
cases to death
in which case they just cremate them and
throw them away
but we have a right to know this
information it was only Julian Assange
who gave it to us for that we should be
grateful
I also want to talk about the kinds of
conditions that Julian might face would
face will face when he uh if he's
extradited to the United States and
convicted
I want to come back to my initial
statement that the government is lying
we know about this provisional promise
to not send Julian to uh to a Sam unit
there are other units called cmus
communication management units there's
also solitary confinement
it is not up to the prosecutors in any
case
to decide who goes to what prison and
who is kept in what unit they have
literally no say on the matter the judge
has no say on the matter
the only people who get to decide that
are the senseless bureaucrats in the
Federal Bureau of Prisons and even if
they decide not to send Julian to a
restricted unit
all that has to happen for him to go
there is for any random prisoner to walk
up to a prison guard and say I just
heard two people talking about stabbing
Julian Assange
then Julian will be sent to solitary
confinement indefinitely for his own
safety
when I first arrived at prison
I decided to file a Freedom of
Information Act request about myself and
the reason I did this is because I had
begun writing an open letter from prison
that I called letter letters from
Loretto
it enraged the warden and so I would
smuggle these letters out to my attorney
and then she would send them to the
media and they were getting millions and
millions of hits and so I was put in
what was called a modified
Communications management unit there was
a five-day delay on my incoming and
outgoing emails my phone calls were not
recorded they were listened to live by a
live guard
and uh and both my incoming and outgoing
mail was uh was opened and read
so in this
in this modified CMU all of a sudden I
felt my style cramped so I wrote a
letter to the Bureau of Prisons and I
said uh under the Freedom of Information
Act I request all documents that you
have on John kiriaku
and um
much to my surprise about six weeks
later I got a package 220 Pages 200
pages of it was nonsensical my medical
records my visitors list things that
nobody can nobody cared about but there
were 20 pages that were very clearly
stamped at the top and the bottom
foia exempt do not release to inmate so
either someone in the Bureau of Prisons
foia office was brain dead or they took
pity on me and decided uh you know I
should probably see this
what it was was a series of memos that
the warden was sending out to prison
guards preparing them for my arrival the
one that was the most fun for me was one
page with very large
print large fonts and it said caution
inmate has access to the media
imagine Jillian Assange
he won't be in any modified CMU he'll be
in the CMU now there are two cmus in the
United States one is in the former death
row at the maximum security penitentiary
in Terre Haute Indiana the other is at
the supermax prison in Marion Illinois
both of these prisons are hell on Earth
and I'll tell you about that in a moment
but when these when these communications
management units were set up in the
1980s they were meant to house the most
dangerous criminals that were in the
American prison system and I'm talking
about the last surviving member of the
Abu nidal terrorist organization a
terrorist who blew up an Egypt airplane
that killed something like 183 people uh
the the so-called blind Shake Omar
abdulrahman who was sort of the The
Godfather of the first attack on the
World Trade Center
that's not really the case anymore
now the CMU houses
a medical whistleblower by the name of
Marty goddessfeld it houses the the
famed drone whistleblower Daniel
um
Daniel Daniel Hale thank you Daniel Hale
uh
it houses environmental activists
this isn't why cmus were created but
this is what they're going to do with
Julian and why are they going to do with
Julian because they don't want him to
tell anybody what he knows and he knows
a lot
he knows a lot about crimes that have
been committed by the American
government war crimes and crimes against
humanity so when they say that he'll be
treated fairly
it's a lie he won't be treated fairly
I'm going to repeat something that I say
a lot too about the court in which
Julian would be tried were he to be
extradited this is the eastern district
of Virginia this is the court that I was
tried in the court that CIA
whistleblower Jeffrey Sterling was tried
in it's the court that Ed Snowden has
been charged in
there's a judge there well there are a
couple of Judges the one that that did
my case in Jeffrey Sterling's and
everybody else's uh judge leonie
brinkama used to reserve all of the uh
National Security cases for herself and
no National Security defendant has ever
won a case there
well she's not Julian's judge Julian's
judge would be
the chief judge and what did he do
before he was the chief judge he was a
judge on the fisa court
that is the court that is so secret that
we don't even really know what they do
that's who's going to try Julian now in
my case my best friend's wife had an
uncle who was O.J Simpson's jury
consultant
most of you I would assume know who O.J
Simpson was football player actor most
likely double murderer and um and they
won the case
so this jury consultant offered to help
me for free
he flew up to Washington we got him a
security clearance and he went through
fifteen thousand pages of classified
Discovery and in the end he told me that
if we were in any other District in
America
he would say let's go for it we're going
to win this case
but he said the eastern district of
Virginia
your jury is going to be made up of
people from or with relatives at the CIA
the Pentagon the FBI the Department of
Homeland Security and dozens of National
Security and intelligence contractors he
said my friend you don't have a chance
and that's why I ended up taking a plea
now
I was charged with Espionage three
counts but I hadn't committed Espionage
and so they dropped those charges
they're not offering Julian a sweetheart
deal
they've made this as difficult as they
possibly could from the very beginning
of the case
there's really no reason
for us to think well you know
they've made their point and Julian's a
journalist even they have to agree with
that it's not going to be as bad no no
it's it's bad as we think it is
when the CIA comes up with a plot to
murder Julian in the Streets of London
in broad daylight
because they don't like the journalism
that he's doing
that's a problem
so I wanted to say again
that Julian's case is bigger than Julian
Assange
this is a case about the rule of law
it's a case about the Constitution it's
about the way the United States presents
itself to the rest of the world
the United States professes to be a
shining Beacon of Hope
for human rights
and civil rights and civil liberties
and the rule of law and that's just
simply not true
it's not
and that's why we have to stand up and
stand together because the case isn't
about Julian it's about all of us
thank you very much
thank you